

MACHINE LEARNING SCIENTIST · SOFTWARE ENGINEER · PHD (COMPUTER SCIENCE)

Amsterdam. The Netherlands

☐ dmalt | ☐ dmitrii-altukhov-258b05233 | ☑ altukhov.dm@gmail.com | ☐ +316 136 36 770

Profile _

I specialize in software engineering and data science with 8-years experience building data analysis algorithms. This involves using existing **machine learning**, **statistical analysis** and **linear algebra** techinques, as well as developing custom tools and algorithmic solutions.

Technologies: Python, C/C++, Java

Experience ____

Artificial Intelligence Research Institute (AIRI)

Moscow, Russia

RESEARCH FELLOW

Feb. 2022 - Apr. 2023

- Built and trained deep learning model to predict speech from MEG data in **PyTorch** in a multi-GPU cloud-based setup
- Developed real-time pipeline for EEG timeseries analysis using Python

Higher School of Economics, Centre for Cognition and Decision Making

Moscow, Russia

JUNIOR RESEARCH FELLOW

Feb. 2017 - Dec. 2021

- Curated and published MEG dataset for metacognition research using BIDS and OpenNeuro
- · Led 4-people group developing software for real-time feature extraction and 3D visualization of brain activity from EEG in Python
- Sped up by a factor of 10 the beamformer inverse solver in MNE-python by modifying the algorithm for vectorized computations

Higher School of Economics, Faculty of Computer Science

Moscow, Russia

SENIOR LECTURER

Aug. 2019 - Dec. 2021

• Developed and taught a course "MATLAB for data analysis" to undergraduate students

University of Montreal, CERNEC lab.

Montreal, Canada

VISITING RESEARCHER, TEMPORARY POSITION

Oct. - Dec. 2015, May 2016 - Dec. 2016

- Built a classifier for ASD patients vs. Controls with 75% accuracy using classical ML and information geometry in **Python**
- Co-developed an open-source **Python** package for heavy neuroimaging data processing, Neuropycon, Meunier et al. [2020]

Moscow State University for Pedagogics and Education, MEG Center

Moscow, Russia Feb 2015 - Dec 2018

JUNIOR RESEARCH FELLOW

• Published two papers in international collaboration with the University of Montreal, see Alamian et al. [2017a,b]

Scientific Research Institute of System Analysis

Moscow, Russia

RESEARCH ASSISTANT, PROMOTED TO JUNIOR RESEARCH FELLOW

Jun. 2011 - Jan. 2015

- $\bullet \ \ \text{Validated commercial software for simulations of flow in jet engines by comparing simulated vs. theoretical shock wave parameters$
- Developed a droplet evaporation model in C++

Education

Ph.D. in Computer Science

Moscow, Russia

HIGHER SCHOOL OF ECONOMICS, FACULTY OF COMPUTER SCIENCE

Jan. 2016 - Nov. 2021

- Thesis: "Optimal methods for functional connectivity estimation in magnetoencephalography."; GPA: 4.0
- Published a paper in a leading neuroscientific journal (see Ossadtchi et al. [2018]) by proposing an algorithm for brain signals analysis.
 Implementation in MATLAB integrated with C++

Ph.D. in Computational Fluid Dynamics (unfinished, transferred to CS program)

Moscow, Russia

LOMONOSOV MOSCOW STATE UNIVERSITY, DEPARTMENT OF MECHANICS AND MATHEMATICS

Sep. 2013 - Jan. 2016

• Thesis: "Numerical simulations of reactive gas flows."

Specialist degree in Mechanics (Masters equivalent)

Moscow, Russia

Sep. 2008 - Jun. 2013

LOMONOSOV MOSCOW STATE UNIVERSITY, DEPARTMENT OF MECHANICS AND MATHEMATICS

• Thesis: "Enhancement and validation of LOGOS software for simulations of the reactive fluid flows."

Honors & Awards

• Selected together with other 178 people across the university for 2-year Higher School of Economics Moscow, Russia Academic Scholarship for publishing a paper in a high-impact journal • Selected 1-st out of 5 teams together with 2 teammates in IEEE Brain Data Bank Challenge for building a St. Petersburg, Russia

competitive 2-players drinking game based on brain-computer interface

Conference contributions

POSTER PRESENTATIONS

Biomag 2022 Birmingham, UK OVERT SPEECH DECODING FROM MEG DATA DECONTAMINATED FROM ARTICULATION ARTIFACTS Philadelphia, USA Biomag 2018 OBLIQUE PROJECTION FOR PHASE SHIFT INVARIANT IMAGING OF COHERENT SOURCES **Tubingen Systems Neuroscience Symposium 2018** Tubingen, Germany OPTIMIZED PROJECTION FOR ZERO PHASE LAG CONNECTIVITY ESTIMATION 2018 Philadelphia, USA Biomag 2018 NEUROPYCON: A PYTHON PACKAGE FOR EFFICIENT MULTI-MODAL BRAIN NETWORK ANALYSIS 2018 **5th Workshop on Optically-Pumped Magnetometers** Freiburg, Switzerland OPM vs. SQUID ARRAYS IN MEG FUNCTIONAL CONNECTIVITY ESTIMATION Biomag 2016 Seoul, South Korea POWER AND SHIFT INVARIANT IMAGING OF COHERENT SOURCES BY MEG DATA 2016 **Brain Connectivity Workshop 2015** San Diego, USA

TALKS

Samara, Russia International conference "Brain-Computer Interface: Science and Practice" COGNIGRAPH: A REAL-TIME EEG-BASED SOURCE IMAGING SOFTWARE 2019 Comprehensive training "MEG at McGill" Montreal, Canada MEG RESTING-STATE IN AUTISM. APPROACH TO ANALYSIS. 2015

Selected Publications _____

GLOBALLY-OPTIMIZED POWER AND SHIFT INVARIANT IMAGING OF COHERENT SOURCES

- 1. Dmitrii Altukhov, Daria Kleeva, and Alexei Ossadtchi. PSIICOS projection optimality for EEG and MEG based functional coupling detection. BioRxiv, 2023
- 2. V. Manyukhina et al. Globally elevated excitation-inhibition ratio in children with autism spectrum disorder and below-average intelligence. Molecular Autism, 2022
- 3. B. Martín-Luengo et al. Retrospective confidence judgements in general-knowledge questions. PsyArXiv, 2021
- 4. D. Meunier et al. NeuroPycon: An open-source python toolbox for fast multi-modal and reproducible brain connectivity pipelines. NeuroImage, 2020
- 5. E. Combrisson et al. Visbrain: A multi-purpose GPU-accelerated open-source suite for multimodal brain data visualization. Frontiers in Neuroinformatics, 13, 2019
- 6. A. Ossadtchi, D. Altukhov, and K. Jerbi. Phase shift invariant imaging of coherent sources (PSIICOS) from MEG data. NeuroImage, 183, 2018
- 7. Z. Yaple et al. Power of feedback-induced beta oscillations reflect omission of rewards: evidence from an EEG gambling study. Frontiers in Neuroscience, 12, 2018
- 8. G. Alamian et al. Alterations of Intrinsic Brain Connectivity Patterns in Depression and Bipolar Disorders: A Critical Assessment of Magnetoencephalography-Based Evidence. Frontiers in Psychiatry, 8(March), 2017a
- 9. G. Alamian et al. Measuring alterations in oscillatory brain networks in schizophrenia with resting-state MEG: State-of-the-art and methodological challenges. Clinical Neurophysiology, 128(9), 2017b
- 10. N. Smirnov et al. Supercomputer simulations of detonation of hydrogen-air mixtures. International Journal of Hydrogen Energy, 2015
- 11. V. Betelin et al. Supercomputer modeling of hydrogen combustion in rocket engines. Acta Astronautica, 2012

2019

2015